Okay, so let's discuss
Monte Carlo analysis, at
least what you need to
know for the PMP exam.
Okay, I'm just going to discuss the level
of detail that you need for the exam.
Now, Monte Carlo, then, is a random
iterative compute model, right?
He uses a whole series of probability
distributions.
Alright, so in an early video then, we
talked about three-point estimating, right?
And in three-point estimating,
you get your optimistic, most-like,
pessimistic figures, right,
and then come up with
a pert estimate and so
and so and so forth, right?
Now, we were just talking about one
particular activity, and even with one
particular activity, you're
not just necessarily going to
have one optimistic, one most
likely, one pessimistic figure.
I mean, first of all, why do we have
optimistic, most likely pessimistic figures?
Well, because of some
kind of uncertainties, some
kind of risks that can
happen on your project.
So if this happens, then it'll take us
this much time.
time.
If this happens, it might take us this
much time.
So you're not just going
to have one risk on your
project, you're going to have
many risks, multiple risks.
So you may have multiple optimistic,
most likely pessimistic figures, right?
So, and for each activity, right?
So for one activity, you may have maybe
five, 10, 15, even, right, optimistic,
most likely pessimistic figures,
right?
Now, I mean, maybe not as many as that,
but I mean, or maybe even more.
It all depends on the situation and
scenario, but you may have multiple
optimistic, most likely pessimistic
figures.
That's just for one activity.
Now multiply that by a thousand, two
thousand, however many activities you have.
Now you can see that the whole series of
events that could potentially happen on
your project, whole series of
uncertainties.
And that's where the Monte Carlo comes in,
right?
You plug basically all of these numbers
into a Monte Carlo analysis.
So, It requires having multiple estimates
for each activity, right?
You calculate the three-point estimate,
right, and there might be several
three-point estimates, and then you build
this probability distribution,
and you may get, you may end it with
something like, you know, some kind of
curve like this, some kind of S-curve like
this.
Right, and the way to interpret it,
right, you've got your probability,
right, on the, on the y-axis here,
and you've got, say, in this case,
we're looking at timeline, you've got the
timeline down here on the x.
right and basically you could use this
then so based on all of these
probabilities that we've identified all
these uncertainties right now we can
determine you know the most likely if you
like or now we can determine just some
degree of certainty right when we should
be finishing our project right or what
timeline in this case we should set for
our project what deadline right so for
example if we're thinking
here of 22 weeks what is a
possible possibility of our
project finishing by week 22.
When we look at this, saying, well,
it's just over 20%, right?
Maybe, what, 23%.
Are we very confident?
Do you think we'll be very confident at 22
weeks?
There's only a 23% of us finishing this
project by week 22.
So maybe not.
What we'll be looking at is more of the
80, 85, 90% probability.
So the 85% probability says we might be
finishing between 24.
in 25 weeks.
So that's where we might be setting,
trying to look at our deadline.
Maybe we'll set it round about 24,
24 and a half, 25 weeks, right?
Then we have some level of confidence that
yes, we'll be able to meet that deadline.
So that's just a very, very high level way
of looking at Monte Carlo analysis.
And really about as much
as what you need, about as
much analysis as what you
would need for the PMP exam.